I have been listening probably most of
your talks so I tried to come here a
topic that maybe was not this cuts
directly and maybe will be interesting
to go deeper into it
they are obviously quite spread view
about the idea of me Barnum as being
something positive almost in kind of
heaven or state place to go they even
say you know all its practice together
so we go together to Nibbana sometimes
they don't say such an extreme way but
definitely you can see the ideas in
views have elements of that kind of
permanent space of permanent stage where
you go and of course is also becoming
some kind of position kind of saying no
it is a negative thing and it's right
probably taken again some kind of facts
and arguments to fight against the the
thinkers of positive Nibbana so what you
can say about that one
[Music]
so what do they what what positive
what's negative
so basically positive we can start you
know just what is me bombing is really a
state to goal is it anything positive
about it because I'm exceptions well
yeah since you don't have any specific
misconceptions questions I'll just tell
you understanding me banner so absence
of passion as a more than being is when
the band-aids
so absence of possibility of passion
absence of possibility of aversion
possibility of distraction and delusion
so it's you can take to be positive you
can take to be negative take immature we
want if you take it to be absence of
these three things straight so they're
not a mystical state instead another
state that happens to you in a sense of
why this experience must have been
abandoned it's a state to develop by
removing greed aversion and delusion
entirely from all layers of your
experience so this new bona why you the
bully still here and then putting me
bona well if you understand the ban
about the body is still here alive then
you know what for anyone is addressed or
parinibbana when person doesn't have any
Varna it's meaningless
so you know right now confirm or deny
that this in kind of state you can still
feel like sense of experience this sense
of experience environment five bigots so
what do you mean you cannot confirm or
deny that it sustained
so anybody wouldn't be thinking of other
death this is this kind of continuity
that you still experience something well
saying there is continuity order the
reason continuity is meaningless to the
mind that doesn't even have the right
view let alone Nirvana because any idea
of saying what after implies after which
means it's already form continuity even
if you say there is nothing after the
fact that the person thinks they can
think after is nothing that's already
something for them yes I mean it's not
like it's a state in as much as you can
remove this a state so what do you think
no because Nibbana
I don't think so even the word says is
in a kind of state it just means ending
of something like extension ending of
power you know something which I assume
is there could see when one sees through
it you know how can I be there that's a
still experience without being without
being affected by some assumptions well
if it's Nibbana state is a power say
Nibbana is extinction of power its
extinction of being it's still something
as such I can even talk about it how can
you in for it talking experience it if
it's not a state
well pneumonic can be never really in
front of you it's not a thing that well
more like let's say context well in that
sense nothing can be in front of you
know is your being is your power in
front of you
baba is Bauer something in front of you
or is in your context I would say the
power mama eats more
he's your being something you can attend
to I would say yes if you're attending -
that's not a being that's on account of
you being being your being is already
where your situation is so you can
attend on account of it but you cannot
attend it because you are it because
it's like saying your I can attend to
itself so it was like being in a sense
in the front like it's conceived it's
the English conceived but the conceiving
does not happen in front of you the
conceiving is not a matter of choice an
intention and attention so conceiving is
the direct result of lacking that
understanding of that fundamental
context yes
so perceiving is already conceiving yes
so that's why I thought like not knowing
not recognizing the the context mm-hmm
so not having stem in the right context
and saying about this thing's not having
these things right viewer I took is a
context and view or something which is
let's say reading and Imbaba
something in front yeah but you can
already see that's not quite adequate
because why would the being just simply
being there regardless of the content
why would that be the content of your
context that's the whole point of being
it's nonspecific not not bound to this
to that just the fact that you are means
that's what being is so if nib on is
extinction of that that's what I mean so
in that sense even that being cannot be
in front of you so what is Nibbana them
if being cannot be in front of you what
would then constitute extinguishing of
that being
I'll take the goods yeah okay but let's
keep it within this no just no I do not
sell fire okay fire it so so if being is
always on the level of the context your
being here and now what would be
extinguishing with that
what would you extinguish there's
extinguishing of the context mean there
is no context no it is impossible
exactly so it's impossible then for me
bana to not be an experience
yes experience although this is what
about the giggles yeah let's again stay
with the beam so the being that cannot
be in front of you you extinguish the
context of that being and that cannot be
in front of it but is it correct and to
say that that's not that that's like a
not a special experience so that or
that's a special experience so that
oh well that cannot be sort of
experience in the same sense as powers
cannot be directly or indirectly
experienced which one is it
how can there be extinguishing of your
being unless that's also your situation
at the time but there's no anymore
discount receiving of me and the world
so you just experience as it is okay so
suddenly Bernie's experience Nirvana is
experience so what's the difference then
between the experience of Nirvana and
experience of non Nibbana the one is
well I can
I deal from ibama know conceived
affected by illusion sorry nany Barney's
more of an idea of Nirvana no new bomber
me Barney's more of an idea of Nirvana
what does it mean
so I'm lost
so if the again let's practically
speaking the current context of your
situation in the most general terms you
are doesn't matter what you are does
matter higher doesn't matter even how
you conceive yourself to be means you
are there first you have some general
sense of hearing now yes extinguishing
of that it's not extinguishing of this
particular conceiving of that particular
problem it's extinguishing with you being given
it's extinguishing with you being given
now it's just experience
so if hearing now as a most fundamental
general context these experience what
would then be the extinguishing of it
without sort of destroying it because
obviously destruction of hearing now is
not Nibbana either what are the
assumptions about experience such as
assumptions that I'm control things the
things up for me
well where are those assumptions is
there something you can see directly
obviously not because if you see
directly then you see me yours
extinguishing of those assumptions what
does that entail like you can well you
can you can extinguish the assumption of
I am and still not being Ivana which
means my extinguishing I am contain
something that pertains to Nibbana but
it's not sufficient in itself like
abandoning art Avada does not take you
to Nevada still this kind of sense of
control so they still yes what is it
that's in common to all those
assumptions that you want to extinguish
what is the more fundamental thing
that's present in them that you do
extinguish the extinguishing assumptions
they then basically establishes
experience of Nirvana
sure greed aversion and delusion always
so can you have sense of self can you
have a sense of control can you have any
form of implicit desire you can't
impossible so then the extinguishing of
being it's not the extinguishing of here
and now that it is its extinguishing of
greed aversion delusion within here and
now and that's when the burner becomes
visible here and now not because he was
elsewhere and then you brought it into
here and now is a special experience
that sort of you haven't understood at
the time but he was sober whelming it
must have been right and then you
figured it out later
that's mysticism you brought it here and
now cuz he was always here and now he
was being obscured you remove the
obscurities that's how you you get to
experience it that's a good river to
like Nibbana dot the element of Nirvana
means the possibility of Nibbana is
always here and now because the
possibility of abandoning greed aversion
erosion is always here enough so can you
find greed aversion delusion anyone else
anywhere else apart from your feeling no
impossible so understanding the context of the
so understanding the context of the
feeling then understanding the nature of
the feeling remove the assumptions about
it removes the basis for any desire no
it's the feeling which then stops
feeling the assumption but it's not like
you choose to remove this assumption you
it's indirect in a sense of you discern
what the basis for assumption is which
is lacking the knowledge of the nature
of the present enduring feeling and by
developing that basis or rather by
removing the basis which is lacking of
the knowledge so by replacing the basis
of liking with the knowledge lacking of
the knowledge replacing it with the
knowledge you have removed the basis for
four assumptions so that's our
assumptions were seized so that's when
Ivana is determined innocent in that
indirect sense yes it's determined upon
your effort went
your effort to develop my banner and
that's why again that's why I say
Nibbana is not a special non experience
occurring between experience and on
experience that kind of overrides
everything else new bond is also one of
the dumbest like everything every
context Julian it's a form of Dhamma to
form phenomena it's where your mind is
and Nibbana is also so the only
difference between Nibbana
Dhamma and any other non Limbaugh Dharma
is whether it's determined by greed
aversion delusion where is determined by
the ground water weather is determined
by the liking of the understanding of
feeling when did he tell me by any
approach that refining the suitors so
then also authentic shift even know
exactly what would make him angry but he
doesn't get angry it's the way he could
know exactly what used to make him angry
yeah because what used to make him last
for were used to make him distracted I
just remember there was one incident I
think with Adam Shaw and ask him he gets
angry in the way he said apparent with
something like yes but I don't pick it
up right in the sense like maybe uh
maybe command I recognize what can annoy
me what may be with me angry but yeah
yeah yeah it could mean there is a
degree of disagreeable but I'm not
picking it up but it can also mean oh I
choose to not pick it up
which means you you are affected by it
so yes it's a good thing that you don't
pick it up but that's not enough you
also want to not be affected by it
the same we desire probably yeah so so
you can see even the Buddha recognized
what's beautiful thing during the world
doesn't make doesn't fit why is that
because he does just fundamental things
he sees that he feeling us feeling so
why this beauty why does the book that
doesn't have why does he doesn't what
why does he lack desire towards
beautiful things
why is there no desire to beautiful
things just general recognizing that he
letting go of control because his eyes
exactly trying to control your feelings
well feelings in its own nature rising
and ceasing while the petitioner strike
two I think people can recognize it I have
I think people can recognize it I have
control and then have desire in regard
to not having control anything can be
taken by desire but some people find the
thrill find the desire in not having
control in submitting they'll control
they find pleasurable so it's not that
because if they were containing the
desire then those people would not be
able to experience these I don't know
kind of non control yet they do but why
doesn't the good experience desire to
its beautiful things in the world
time for disappears why because time is
painful well again if that's all it
takes they would be note on huh if B if data
they would be note on huh if B if data
is painful you're automatically be free
from down because the whole purpose of
pathogen is to avoid pain and not want
to better not give in to pain so you
can't be there either so why does the
Buddha have no desire towards beautiful
things in the world
you know how to answer otherwise I chose
this kind of assumption disappears and
well all those are kind of theoretical
answers yes well it doesn't answer it
assumption is appear ok why does the
assumption disappear
why is there no desire to it's beautiful
things in the world for mind it's fully
awakened all for a mind it beyond
sensuality
because what an assumption about me and
the world disappears and okay yeah he
does it why does that assumption
disappear yes this again will be
theoretically yeah so why does the image
disappear it's militarized so yeah that's a good
it's militarized so yeah that's a good
knowledge rise why there's the knowledge
right no so only those like there's no
like romances but that is not accurate
enough answer so that's the whole story
let's let's dig so why does the
knowledge arise in regard to beautiful
things so there is no desire what is the
knowledge you know got to beautiful
things so there is no desire to work
them
I do have answers keeps coming up but I
know that wouldn't be the answer
I think okay tell me well no it can't
defeats the purpose yes
okay give some other answer that comes
to mind doesn't matter if it's not
accurate enough
so understanding the whole nature as a
whole when it's also understanding they
actually nothing to read these things
when its own the things already
the term this really kind of given
beforehand but actually convene can
really control over those things but all
of that is kind of secondary
psychologizing but providing the reasons
to yourself why you shouldn't do it like
that why you should not have desire you
know it's because of this is because of
this is because of this none of any
single tenuously scene is an underlying
cause because of which will be unable to
experience desire towards it so what is
like people are this what is singleton
is the present in every experience of
beautiful on account of which you can
experience non desire really because
which the second question yeah so let's
let's do it again
so like experience a beautiful like
beautiful sight yes and there is a
desire to watch it that's the starting
point so you don't approve that desire
by providing explanations why that's not
right while it's not beautiful why they
so like that that's you trying to manage
your desire so direct insight requires
you to see through that which is
beautiful towards which you have desire
so there's a result of that direct
seeing there is no desire not as the
result of your effort to cover up desire
or to manage it or to explain it so you
become unable to have desire towards it
that's what knowledge of beautiful means
so I'm asking you what is that knowledge
of beautiful they will result in you
being unable to have desire in the same
sense as the Buddha said you will be
unable to have desire towards the food
you just vomited yes just because you
see it's not so pleasant as your what it
is you see there's not so pleasant it's
not listen because you see solid bodies
not Duke of edenia
what is it ok Duke is I mean what is it
look in that particular case not general
what toka the determination is dukkha
so what is the termination beautiful
that is dukkha the I lost no result of
an ignorance so what is the timid
determination of beautiful that when not
known you have desire towards it
we're known you don't have desire
towards it feeling well this material
shapes perception perception yeah but
what kind of perception beautiful is a
perception so what determination
beautiful is beautiful don't think about
it threateningly
think about it through the experience of
something beautiful recollect something
beautiful that you had desired two words
now obviously you don't act Oh
so sensory strain is there
they established beforehand so now in
the experience of beautiful that you
have desired towards I want to see what
is that determination yeah you were
right you wanna count of which you will be
you wanna count of which you will be
unable to maintain that desire it's not
like I'll see this and then I'll say no
to my desire that's not accurate it has
beautiful experiences when normal
language would say like us experiences
about thing yeah okay sure the memory so
whatever take a memory take whatever not
me so it's a it's a memory of a
beautiful experience which arise so not
as we do what is beautiful in that I'm
asking you what is determining that
beautiful what is the necessary base but
what is it what is the center of that
beautiful could you brought it up
so is the other hand what is beautiful
so I can say this ignorance or something
else butit who is beautiful exactly so
so that's why I asked why does the
Buddha doesn't know why doesn't in our
hand to see the beautiful nothing more
there is no desire towards beautiful now
because he always needs to explain
himself why this is not worth desiring
in just simply has no desire towards it
in the same sense you don't need to
explain yourself why you shouldn't eat
your vomit
you just want because it's disgusting
so what's in every heart or beautiful
what's in heart of every experience a
beautiful what is that it's a meal isn't
it well yeah see Pleasant dissolve more
with okay no that's all it the response
to being misperceived is beautiful so
what is beforehand what is not
beforehand in the sense of what was
before you know what is as you said what
is the determination of it that if you
can see correctly you will not have
desire towards it
think of it okay let's say that similar
discussion let's say this simile for the
soda no not quite
the beautiful tasty beverage perfect in
taste color smell beautiful drink in
every regard yes with poison but you
don't know this poison there so you
fully gripped by the desire to consume
that drink so you pull it it's beautiful
and this desire to is that beautiful to
its consumption towards engaging with it
so then you find out there is a poison
in it so the drink hasn't changed
no your perception of it hasn't changed
just it's still the same smell taste
touch the same consistency but now you
have no desire to vote it poison so
what's the poison other contexts did you
see some kind of danger you see in it so
it's dangerous
yes so now the same thing through the
heart of the same drink still in front
of you can still smell it you see that
it's dangerous if you engage with it and
that's sufficient for you to not have
desire towards it right so it's the
danger they will prevent you from having
desire towards it but not danger in a
sense you've been doing like explaining
the danger psychologize in the danger
and saying because this is not in my
control because of this because of this
because of this all that's true
theoretically but none of that can serve
the basis for you uprooting the desire
because that danger needs to be seen
through that thing that is beautiful not
in response to not after or before or
whatever else so if you the heart of
every beautiful
dangerous you cannot possibly want it it
would be inconceivable to have desire
towards it regardless the extent of the
beauty heavenly beauty like the
factually absolutely like the most
refined beauty you can imagine it's
equally dangerous it's still pretty
shares the same nature and that's why
the mind who is fully awakened will not
have any desire not just towards these
swirly things but even you know the
ideas of heavens or even experiences or
whatever Davers and so on he just cannot be
Davers and so on he just cannot be
wanted because any form of beauty is
dangerous in that sense why is it
dangerous what is the danger well first things I
what is the danger well first things I
would say that so again keep the same
principle in mind beautiful within
beautiful you see dangerous now further
putting beautiful that it's dangerous
what else do you see as characteristics
of that same thing that present enduring
because more your because it it's my
sister these things is dangerous and
then keep gratifying that object it's
just like you also gratifying the whole
assumption about the link you're not
aware of any of those things when you're
engaging gratification so now they can
play the part but what is their apparent
in that danger but what is there they
can be apparent in that danger in other
words what are the characteristics of
danger why is danger dangerous dangerous
why is danger dangerous dangerous
because you may be you are loving no
soon as you started with maybe it's not
gonna be an accurate answer because now
you're trying to figure it out not
trying to describe take the experience
of danger any danger and look for what
is the nature of being exposed to danger
you have no control you have no control
you start losing it you okay so I'm a
second slave enslaved okay I thought you
said something else
so danger implies not control now you
ask yourself further is non control
always unpleasant
no no exactly so what other things are
there free good day they're always
present in dangerous so take that non
control further why is that non control
dangerous gratification still there no
wise don't think about gratification now
I'm asking you why is danger dangerous
you said cause it's not he has no
control okay so why is the non control
dangerous what's the difference between
non dangerous not control and dangerous
not control in other words was
definitely in danger and on danger you
know when dangerous becomes when goes
against your own desire in preferences
your expectations yes but not accurate
enough not enough its pleasant I can
imagine you're on the you were exposed
to some danger now why why is that
danger what is the nature of danger
that's the definition of painful why is
it painful and you can all see the same
things losing control well but then I'm
just revolving around it's like so why
is not having control that's a
characteristic pain that's a
characteristic why doncha that's
characteristic so to speak what do these
things have in common
whatever says whatever comes to mind look
look
non accurate answer is not a wrong
answer and by providing an accurate
answer and you define what's more
accurate than that it will be the
question again yeah so what's in common
to the two danger no control and
unpleasantness of it what's the common
characteristic what's the unifying
characteristic that makes danger
dangerous that makes danger unpleasant maybe not
that makes danger unpleasant maybe not
able to face it's impermanent it's so
it's there's no permanent it and there
it is so what is safety
yes so what is the characteristic Bend
of non safety if you don't feel safe
it's a lack of safety defines what's
dangerous yes
so if things are safe they are
automatically not dangerous even if you
don't think about safety any experience
of danger means it's a threat means you
are subjected to it and yes it means you
have no control and it means that threat
is already unpleasant even if the danger
is far removed not like a acuity mediate
the fact that it brings the glimpse of
ultimately you around the threat your
life is under threat your life can end
things that you hold to be yours can be
swept away that the recognition the
holding that's why it's dangerous so
those are the characteristics you want
to see in beautiful objects in the world
like safety threat danger nor control
directly while they're present not in
response to them as a management
technique so that I mean you need like
people need to learn how to learn things
to endure and then see through them what
else is simultaneously very enduring
because again you wouldn't be talking
about characteristics of danger when
danger is gone
because then it becomes a Napster thing
no you discern the danger and then you
can discern the simultaneous
characteristics that define that danger
so why is then lack of safety why is
that unpleasant and unwanted why did the
first sense of safety the kind of
nonsense because like you know the whole
assumption I am is going to be feeling
of dying and anyone to protect it I mean
you don't even know it's just us yeah
you don't think those things are new
things that you do think which is why do
you value safety why safety more
desirable they're not simply isn't
comfortable its pleasant and comfortable
so why is then the pleasure more wanted
and this pleasure not wanted because
they give us pleasure using more assumed
confirmation that they're safe safety
well no that's the result of you want in
that pleasure so why do you want
pleasure and not want pain
why do you act towards protecting a
pleasure in a back towards avoiding pain
there is no reason that's the whole
point there is no reason why you prefer
pleasure on account of pain and that's
why you automatically do so you don't
know that there is no reason and that's
how that becomes your reason if you
suddenly record or not sudden if you
make the effort to go like this and
discern the various categories they will
bring you back right to the starting
point of oh so all I'm doing is trying
to avoid pain and prompt pleasure and
I've absolutely no justification for
that there is no reason you just choose
to act like that for a gratuitous
assumption because that's what you
wanted and that's why it's possible to
undo it see if the reason for your
craving towards feeling of pleasure or
toward feeling of pain afterwards
neutral feeling would be rooted in
feeling or something other you wouldn't
be able to uproot it but it's not rooted
in anything it's always a
Judis response in regard to what you
present a feeling that's what we the
same ignorant is utterly completely
beginningless craving is completely
beginningless because it's not in the
aggregate it's not the result of
aggregates moving and coming together or
whatever no it's just experience of
aggregates means you create the world
against or kind of away from them and
there is no reason for that and until
you find out that there is no reason for
that that will be your reason for
maintaining that craving and that's it
if you're free from craving you cannot
possibly be acting towards on account of
a feeling if you don't like to know kind
of how you feeling you cannot possibly
be exposing yourself to threat of danger
non dangerous safety non safety if
you're not exposing to the threat of
that means you have no desire towards
things that are kind of offering your
safety could you don't buy your safety
anymore because you realize it wasn't
safety and that's the whole point
sensuality and pleasure is the safety
for unlined to mind that's a good asset
to to Gina when touch ground present
feeling doesn't know any other way of
dealing of overcoming of not being
affected by that discomfort except
trying to go into central desire in
response cavalry up it's the only form
of safety he knows and then for as long
as you don't question that form of
safety and see there's known safe
inherently dangerous
you will always regard have a view that
it's safe that is desirable that it's
wanted that it should be obtained but if
in the heart of that safety of sudden
realize oh my goodness this is a trap
see oh there's a safe space for you come
in come in so I can sort of trap you in
and kill you and if that danger becomes
apparent in that safety you realize this
is not safety and you would not have to
you wouldn't need to then explain to
yourself why you shouldn't have desire
automatically you will not have desire
anymore because it's dangerous